Finding Aid for Eugene Gressman papers, 1935-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eugene Gressman papers 1935-1967
Gressman, Eugene, 1917-
1 linear feet
851417 Aa 2
Law clerk to U.S. Supreme Court Justice Frank Murphy, and Washington, D.C. attorney. Diary, 1943-1944, relating to the Supreme Court, and miscellaneous notes, correspondence and newspaper clippings; also papers of Justice Murphy collected by Gressman, including notes of cabinet meetings, and of conferences and telephone calls; and correspondence, 1937-1949, between Frank Murphy and Felix Frankfurter.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Judge Eugene Gressman (donor no. 1088 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Eugene Gressman was born April 18, 1917 in Lansing, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan (A.B., 1938; J.D., 1940). After his admission to the Michigan Bar in 1940, Gressman worked as an attorney with the Securities and Exchange Commission in Washington, 1940-1943. From here, he became law clerk to Supreme Court Justice Frank Murphy, serving from 1943 to 1948. Following Murphy's death, Gressman worked with different Washington law firms.
As a result of his work with Frank Murphy, Gressman became a national authority on practice and procedure before the United States Supreme Court. He was both a writer and teacher on the law. He co-authored the leading lawyers guide to Supreme Court practice and procedure entitled Supreme Court Practice. He has also written articles and pamphlets on the topic, as well as on other federal constitutional and statutory issues. In addition, he has co-authored a constitutional law textbook, and authored part of a treatise on federal jurisdiction. As professor, he has taught courses in constitutional law, federal jurisdiction, professional responsibility and seminars in Supreme Court practice. He has taught some or all of these courses at the North Carolina, Seton Hall, Fordham, Michigan, Ohio State, Indiana at Indianapolis, Catholic and George Washington University law schools.
The collection consists of two kinds of materials: papers of Frank Murphy that Gressman accumulated as clerk to the Supreme Court Justice; and Gressman's own papers. The greater part of the collection are the papers of Frank Murphy, dating from 1935 to 1948, with the bulk of the files falling in the period of 1939 to 1941, when Murphy was US Attorney General and the first year of his tenure on the Supreme Court bench. Always conscious of history, Murphy made valuable notes on the cabinet meetings he attended and his meetings and conversations with various public figures. These individuals include Hugo Black, Louis Brandeis, William J. Donovan, Carter Glass, Charles E. Hughes, Cordell Hull, Joseph P. Kennedy, John L. Lewis, Sir Robert Menzies, Manuel Quezon, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Francis B. Sayre, Harlan F. Stone and Sumner Welles. Also of importance are the several files of letters exchanged between Frank Murphy and Justice Felix Frankfurter.
Gressman's own papers are much smaller, but these also relate to his association with Frank Murphy, including notes that he made preparatory to writing a proposed biography of Murphy. Gressman's diary on his time spent as Murphy clerk of the Supreme Court is dated July 1943 to April 1944.
Subjects:
Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1886-1971.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959.; Glass, Carter, 1858-1946.; Gressman, Eugene, 1917-2010; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969.; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969.; Menzies, Robert Gordon, Sir, 1894-1978.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Sayre, Francis Bowes, 1885-1972.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; United States. Attorney General.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; United States. Supreme Court.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Murphy: Philippine High Commissioner
  - Notes of the Philippine High Commissioner 1935 (Box 1)
  - Notes of the Philippine High Commissioner 1936 (Box 1)
  - Notes from voyage of Frank Murphy from Manila to Detroit May 13, 1936 (Box 1)
- Murphy: Michigan Governor
  - Notes January 11, 1938 of conference between Frank Murphy and President Roosevelt (Box 1)
- Murphy: US Attorney General January 1939-January 1940
  - Copy of letter circa September 1939 from Cliff Prevost concerning Murphy and the Detroit grand jury (Box 1)
  - Notes September 1, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes September 4, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Letter September 4, 1939 from Robert Conway concerning Secretary Hull and German invasion of Poland (Box 1)
  - Notes September 7, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes September 15, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes September 21, 1939 on opening of special session of Congress (Box 1)
  - Notes September 22, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes September 26, 1939 of National Defense Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes September 28, 1939 of Judicial Conference and luncheon at Mrs. E.W. McLean (Box 1)
  - Notes September 29, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes October 2, 1939 of tea with FDR celebrating the 150th Anniversary of the Supreme Court (Box 1)
  - Notes October 5, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes October 13, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes October 19, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes October 26, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes October 27, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes October 31, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes November 1, 1939 of Civil Service Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes November 3, 1939 of meeting with Carter (Box 1)
  - Notes November 3, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes November 7, 1939 of meeting with Swiss Minister, Dr. Charles Bruggman (Box 1)
  - Notes November 9, 1939 of telephone conversation with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes November 10, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes November 11-November 13, 1939 of Langollen weekend (Box 1)
  - Notes November 13, 1939 of telephone conversation with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes November 16, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes November 22, 1939 of conversation with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes November 29, 1939 of luncheon conference with John L. Lewis (Box 1)
  - Notes December 1, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes December 5, 1939 of appointment with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes December 8, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes December 9, 1939 of conference with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes December 14, 1939 of Diplomatic Reception at the White House (Box 1)
  - Notes December 19, 1939, December 28, 1939 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes January 2, 1940 of Presidential press conference and conference with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes January 3, 1940 concerning opening of 77th Congress (Box 1)
  - Notes January 4, 1940 concerning appointment to Supreme Court, and congratulations of Joseph P. Kennedy (Box 1)
  - Notes January 5, 1940 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes January 12, 1940 of Cabinet Meeting (Box 1)
  - Notes January 17, 1940 of conversation with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
- Murphy: US Supreme Court Justice February 1940-1949
  - Notes January-April 1940 of Frank Murphy on Supreme Court activities (Box 1)
  - Notes March 31, 1940 of Frank Murphy, on question of free speech and other freedoms (Box 1)
  - Notes April 2, 1940 of telephone conversation with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes of visit with Justice Brandeis April 19, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Notes October 24, 1940 of conference between President Roosevelt and Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Diary notes November-December 1940 of Frank Murphy, including meetings with Joseph P. Kennedy and Sumner Welles (Box 1)
  - Diary notes 1941 of Frank Murphy, including meetings with President Roosevelt, Felix Frankfurter, R.G. Menzies, Charles Evans Hughes, and Joseph P. Kennedy (Box 1)
  - Notes February 25, 1941 of conference between President Roosevelt and Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Notes May 15, 1941 of visit with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes May 29, 1941 of visit with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes June 4, 1941 of visit with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Notes June 8, 1941 of visit with Col. William J. Donovan (Box 1)
  - Notes June 18, 1941 of luncheon conference between President Roosevelt and Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Telegram June 26, 1941 of President Roosevelt to Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Notes July 18, 1941 of luncheon with President Roosevelt (Box 1)
  - Diary notes 1942 of Frank Murphy, including meetings with President Roosevelt, Harlan Stone, Francis B. Sayre, and Manuel Quezon (Box 1)
  - Notes July 29, 1942 on Supreme Court case concerning President's powers during war time [Ex parte Quirin] (Box 1)
  - Diary notes 1943 of Frank Murphy, including meetings with President Roosevelt and Cordell Hull (Box 1)
  - Notes October 16, 1944 of meeting between President Roosevelt and members of the Supreme Court (Box 1)
  - Notes 1944, 1948 of Justices Hugo Black and Wiley B. Rutledge to Frank Murphy on Supreme Court (Box 1)
- Other Frank Murphy Papers
  - Correspondence between Frank Murphy and Felix Frankfurter 1937-1949, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes and autobiographical material of Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Frank Murphy, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning Frank Murphy (Box 1)
- Eugene Gressman papers
  - Notes undated of Eugene Gressman for use in a proposed biography of Frank Murphy (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1943-1967 of Eugene Gressman (Box 1)
  - Gressman diary, July 1943-April 1944 (Box 1)